Andrew Vallas

Business Development Executive

Philadelphia, PA - Email me on Indeed: indeed.com/r/Andrew-Vallas/4e92b369b70d1463

Internationally experienced BUSINESS DEVELOPER with 28 years experience and a strong background in energy marketing and electricity generation, regulatory affairs, utility operations, and power distribution, . Seeking a challenging position that will utilize my talents.

Willing to relocate: Anywhere

Authorized to work in the US for any employer

WORK EXPERIENCE

Founder - Green Energy Developer

TERRA & FLORESTA DO BRASIL - Salvador, BA - 2004 to Present

- Established a Brazilian corporation and purchased almost 100,000 acres of raw land for charcoal production and timberland development as a green energy fuel source.
- Raised investor capital, obtained licenses, reviewed Brazilian contracts, negotiated local credit lines and registered foreign capital through Central Bank of Brazil.
- Hired and trained 6 technical staff and 40 construction crew workers, oversaw construction and initial operations of various bio-energy projects in extremely remote locations, arranged interstate transportation and sold product to steel producers and soybean crusher (Cargill).
- Projects were licensed and producing up to 10,000 tons of charcoal per year before being sold.

Vice President - Energy Marketing

SEMPRA ENERGY - Toronto, ON - 2001 to 2004

- Developed energy hedging strategies for commercial and industrial clients. Prospected clients, negotiated ISDA Master Agreements and sold financial electricity contracts. Purchased physical electricity.
- As a Minister of Energy appointee to the Independent Electricity System Operator (IESO) Technical Panel, proposed and reviewed amendments to electricity market rules, advised Board on technical issues related to operation of the energy market.
- Made numerous conference presentations representing both the company and the IESO.
- Solely responsible for creating the Ontario Electricity book with a contract value approaching US\$1 billion over 3 years.

Director - Energy Marketing

SEMPRA ENERGY - Atlanta, GA - 2000 to 2001

- Worked on a trading floor and marketed wholesale electricity/natural gas in NY, New England and PJM.
- Negotiated fuel purchases and delivery New England gas and coal power plants
- Determined bid price on Brazilian utility assets.
- Opened the office in Toronto and obtained licenses needed to enter the Ontario electricity market.

Director - Power Plant Operations

CANADIAN NIAGARA POWER - Fort Erie, ON - 1997 to 2000

- Responsible for the operation and maintenance of both a hydroelectric and wind energy generating stations.
- Sold excess energy into New York and Canadian wholesale energy markets.
- Involved in the evaluation of numerous mergers and acquisitions of energy assets including electric generating plants and municipal utilities.

Engineer

NORTHEAST UTILITIES - Berlin, CT - 1987 to 1997

- Designed overhead and underground distribution systems. Determined residential, commercial and industrial loads. Balanced phases, corrected power factor, managed voltage drop. Issued RFPs;
- Supervised union crews during storm restoration. Issued switching, grounding and tagging orders while ensuring adherence to safety procedures.
- Analyzed the worst outages in the entire State and designed improvements to system reliability utilizing reclosers, cutouts, spacer cables, etc. Managed a 10 person engineering team. Reported results to PUC.
- Design system protection from substation to load by coordinating relays, reclosers and cutout fuses.
- Modified substation designs by adding additional transformers and feeders.

Facilities Engineering Intern

IBM CORPORATION - Boca Raton, FL - 1983 to 1986

- Prepared RFPs, held bidder's conferences and awarding contracts for facility construction projects.
- Designed office and lab architectural, electrical and lighting modifications.
- Created a CAD database of facility drawings (architectural, electrical and lighting).
- Liaison between company and contractors for after hour construction.

EDUCATION

MBA in International Finance

NEW YORK UNIVERSITY - New York, NY 1997

MSEE in Nuclear Engineering & Control Theory

RENNSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE - Hartford, CT 1990

BSEE

DREXEL UNIVERSITY - Philadelphia, PA 1987

SKILLS

MS Office (10+ years), Management (10+ years), Business Development (10+ years), Sales (10+ years), Contract Negotiations (10+ years), Commodity Hedging (10+ years)

MILITARY SERVICE

Service Country: US

Branch: US Army Reserves

Rank: Captain

June 1987 to June 1997

3 year R.O.T.C. scholarship recipient

Engineers Officer Basic Course. (covers construction management, critical path planning, estimating, etc.)
Company Commander responsible for over 400 troops

VETERAN - Operation Desert Storm

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

Engineering Skills
Project Management
Power Plant Operations
Power Systems Protection/Relays
Facilities Engineering
Power Distribution

Contract Negotiations NEC, NERC, NESC PUC, PJM, NYISO, NEPOOL MS Office, AutoCAD Energy Marketing